Leah: As we discussed previously, Pair programming is where
two people within a team collaborate and work as a pair.
So how is this different to Mob programming?
With Mob programming the ‘whole team’
works together involving several people.
In this instance the roles of ‘Driver’ and
‘Navigator[s]’ would rotate between the
programmers, and the roles would switch frequently.
One person, the Driver would always write
the code and the other[s] would observe the
code identifying errors and problem solving.
Both Pair and Mob programming practices are
especially useful for sharing knowledge.
So, what are the advantages and
disadvantages of Pair programming?
Chris: Advantages
Pair programming helps to decrease software errors, it
is a less formal review process, and unexpected items
would be noticed quicker from Navigator or Observer.
It helps to improve software quality and
has a ‘positive impact’ on the source code.
It reduces the ‘risk’ of a project especially
if a team member leaves, and experts on specific
subjects can share knowledge with team which
could help to increase the productivity.
It can also help to integrate a new team
member who may have problems with the source
code as they are unfamiliar with the system.
It also helps with different ability levels as a
beginner programmer will increase their productivity
when paired with someone more experienced.
Fatigue can decrease productivity therefore swapping
‘Driver and Navigator roles’ can also increase productivity.
It can help with ‘better team cohesion’ reducing the rate
at which developers exit the team, and it has been found
that pair programming stimulates focus, motivation, and
satisfaction, and is enjoyed for the social dimension.
Leah: Disadvantages
It has been found that it is more useful for
‘complex projects’ but does not add value for
smaller tasks which result in minor bug fixes.
It may increase work time and decrease
productivity as more work hours are spent in pair
programming rather than programming individually.
Some developers need or prefer to work alone, especially
when new and needing to build up skills, confidence,
and self-assurance from producing their own code.
There is also a danger of personality conflict
which could in turn decrease productivity.
It can be time-consuming to setup as communication
mechanisms, objectives, expectations of approach
need to be shared, and continuous feedback is needed.
The Project manager or Developer lead would
need to manage and identify which adjustments
are necessary for the project to be successful.
It may add extra cost to a project as more developer
pairs might be needed to meet tighter deadlines.
Good communication processes and mechanisms in pair
programming are key, because if there are poor standards
or programming practices, and unexpected errors,
code could become disorganised and may need a rework.
Chris: Mob programming
As we have already discussed ‘Mob programming’
is similar to ‘Pair programming’ except
there is one Driver and several Navigators.
The main difference is that the team works together,
and this could include other tasks for the Navigator
roles such as ‘identifying stories’, ‘designing’,
‘testing’, and ‘deployment’ depending on the project.
Leah: Advantages
It has been found that Mob programming
works well for complex software products.
There is better ‘communication and
collaboration’, and the team is self-organised
which works with modern Agile practices.
There is also more ‘Team alignment’ with an ‘increase
in of shared knowledge’, this is especially so where the
team do not have a shared understanding of the project.
Teams have found that mob programming can be fun and
interactive with an improvement of the learning experience.
Mob programming done right can be ‘inclusive’, as
it can provide a safe and encouraging environment
for beginner programmers or new team members.
Chris: Disadvantages
Effects of ‘dominant personalities’ could result in
conflict within a larger team, but also ‘Groupthink’
can occur within a team, where the desire for
harmony results in poor unchallenged decisions.
Mob programming could end up being ‘less productive’ as
it could be difficult to keep focus for the ‘co-pilots’
or ‘navigators’ who aren’t in possession of the keyboard.
There could also be concerns of mangers about
the difficulty of having the whole team working
together for just one element of a project.
Although considered a positive practice Mob programming
still needs more validation through research to
emphasise its benefits and reduce potential risks.